Guide to the Savage Mining Company and Associated Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
The Hale & Norcross ore books (Box 26, folders 393-95) cover the period 1866-74; for 1889-90 the information has been recorded in the Savage ore books (Box 27, folder 439). Ore books record the evaluation of the gold and silver extracted from the mine. Information is arranged by mill, and for each mill there are two sets of listings presented chronologically. The left page gives the number of tickets, weight of the ore, the monetary assay value per ton of gold and silver, the total assay value, and 65 per cent of the assay value (per ton and total). On the right page is listed the bullion returned (bar numbers and amount), the monetary value of gold and silver per bar, total value of each bar, and a grand total. Accounting based on this information shows what is due the mill. At the back of the ore books, a monthly summary gives a mill-by-mill account of "Excess over 65 per cent," "Reclamation," and "Recapitulation from date to date". More detailed information on the mill charges for processing ore can be found in the bullion accounts (Box 26, folders 396-97). Ore assay reports are the first evaluations done on the ore. Hale & Norcross's assays are identical to Savage's but only cover the 1880s (see Box 26, folders 399-422); in fact some of the Savage ore assay reports in 1888 list Hale & Norcross readings. Finally, the ore records for Hale & Norcross include a few monthly statements for the Sutro Tunnel Company for 1884-89. These statements, made by the mines to the tunnel company, suggest that the mining companies contributed to the tunnel based on ore extracted from their own mines. The statements note the tons of ore reduced and at which mill, the bullion yielded and its value, and the dollar figure due the Sutro Tunnel Company; however, the forms are not always completed.
Series III, Ore and Bullion Records, contains evaluations of the Savage mine from extraction through processing to shipment. Taken all together the records are concentrated in the 1860s and 1880s-90s. The Savage ore books (Box 27, folders 434-439), arranged by mill with indexes, bring together data on the cost of production. Information usually noted includes: date of delivery, amount of ore sent, amount of bullion produced, assay values both in terms of fineness and dollars, name of assayer, a certificate number, which links the data to the Memoranda of Bullion (see Box 27-28, folders 440-77), date shipped out and to whom (president in San Francisco), charges (assay, freighting, milling), and the net value of the bullion. There are also summaries at the back of the first two volumes, 1863-65, which report the amount and value of ore produced over time; some summaries emphasized the amount produced for specific periods, others the amount based on the mill.
The Savage's memoranda of bullion (Box 27-28, folders 440-77) are arranged by the names of the assayers and chronologically. The memoranda, which span the period 1863-1873, report the value of the bullion produced and the cost of assaying. Although the forms vary, most note the bar number (which links them to the ore books), weight (sometimes before and after melting), fineness of gold and silver, a number and dollar value, assay charges, and from which mill the bullion came.
The Savage ore assay reports (Box 28-41) were produced daily to monitor the value of the area being mined. They constitute one of the largest series of records in the collection. Although the material dates from 1863 through 1895 and 1914, there are significant gaps, for example, 1871-77. For most of its life, Savage used the Chollar-Potosi Assay Office. Their daily report identified about twenty samples from the mine, stating assay value in dollars for each sample of gold and silver. Starting in 1886, the daily reports are accompanied by forms listing the monetary value of ore labeled "Battery," "Settler," or "Tailings." Following this large series of assay reports are sets of sample assays from cars and mills (Box 41, folders 630-37).
The Savage records in Series III include statements made for the Sutro Tunnel Company, 1880-87, and later the Comstock Tunnel Company, 1891-96 (Box 41, folder 639; Box 86, folder 1419). The collection contains twelve monthly reports for 1892, but for the other years there are only two or three. The statements for the 1880s are identical to those for Hale & Norcross, but the statements in the 1890s are more detailed, providing a good summary of ore-bullion production. They note the weight of ore extracted, shipped, and processed, which mills processed the ore, the weight and value of the bullion, value of bullion sales, and finally the money due the Sutro (later Comstock) Tunnel Company.
Ore-bullion shipment reports for the Savage in Series III document the amount and value of ore shipped to the mills and of the bullion shipped from the mills to San Francisco. The data also includes "Finances at office in San Francisco" which compares the value of bullion to office expenses.
Series IV, Financial Records, is arranged by company; within each company material follows the pattern: ledgers, cashbooks, daybooks, accounts, statements of disbursements, bank records, and receipts. A description of the Savage records will serve as a guide to the others. Special note should be made of the companies not directly involved in mining. There is some data on the finances of the Hillside Water Company, founded by Keating and friends, and further information on the company's accounts can be found in Series I correspondence (see Box 15 for the years 1888-94). M. [Monahan] and Company's (The assumption of the name "Monahan" for "M" is based on the childish scribbling "Katie Monahan" on page 11 of the cashbook and the listing "M. J. Monahan & Company" in a contemporary business directory) ledger and cashbook may be the records of a Virginia City merchant. There is no information in the Pless D. & R. Company bank book to suggest the nature of that business. The material from the M & H Company and R. P. Keating & Company, however, indicates they were involved in the stock market. Financial records involving Savage and another company have been filed under Savage when it is difficult to determine whose copy is in the collection. The same is true for records involving Hale & Norcross.
The Savage records in Series IV have been arranged into three sections: General Records, Superintendent's Records, and Bank Records. General Records house the ledgers, official summaries of the company's financial position, cashbooks, and daily accounts of financial transactions which will be recorded in the ledgers. Ledgers (Box 44, folders 736-41) have indexes by individual and corporate names as well as services or types of accounts. Entries are by function, such as "Assaying Ore," "Office expenses," "Surveying and Drafting," or "President's expense account." For each entry there are two pages with "dr" (debit) on the left, "cr" (credit) on the right, and a chronological listing of transactions underneath. Cashbooks (Box 44, folders 742-53) follow a strict chronological arrangement with entries noting the nature and amount of the bill and in which ledger the bill was later recorded. Once again there are two page spreads, but the "cr" and "dr" are reversed. At the back of the Savage cashbooks is a section entitled "Memorandum," a chronological listing of the monetary value of the bullion from various mills (the money is listed as being in San Francisco office) and "Drafts on [president]," money drawn on the president's account. Following the cashbooks is a daybook, which seems to be a rough draft of a cashbook.
The General Records section ends with a series of receipts for the Savage Mining Company which cover the period 1860-1906 (Boxes 44-57). "Receipts" includes all bills (whether presented by the supplier or Savage's own inhouse copy) recording a transfer of goods or services between Savage and another party. Although the names of the two parties are usually noted, the cost and/or subject of the transaction is not always clear. For some merchants there are monthly reckonings of what Savage purchased. They give an overview of the food, dry goods, and hardware that Savage consumed. The receipts help document Savage's cooperative ventures with other mining companies. In 1896-98, for instance, there are receipts showing Savage's involvement in the Brunswick Exploration Company (see also Box 42, folder 666).
The accounts (Box 58, folders 947-53) in Superintendent's Records are monthly reports that summarize the financial transactions of the office. They note the balances in the timber and lumber, freight, wood, and president's accounts. Drafts on the president and check stubs from an account in the president's name record money paid. The receipt books (Box 59, folders 959-60) document payment made by the Savage superintendent to mills, office personnel, and ore services.
Bank Records contain account books, interest records, checks, and check stubs for Savage bank accounts with B. F. Hastings & Company, Bank of California (Virginia City), Nevada Bank of San Francisco (Virginia City), Paxton & Thornburgh (William Thornburgh, who was involved in the Thornburgh vs. Savage case [see Boxes 7-9], may have been a member of this company), and Wells Fargo & Company.
Series V, Inventory Records, is arranged by company and within each company annual reports precede monthly, weekly, daily records, and general reports precede specific. Only Hale & Norcross and Savage are well documented in this series, and many of the Hale & Norcross records have been filed with the Savage material. The invoice and inventory book (Box 63, folder 1054) contains a variety of records pertaining to Hale & Norcross. There is a listing by company of goods received, a set of annual property inventories for 1875-77, and listings of supplies for special projects.
The inventory records for Savage Mining Company are divided into Savage Assay Office and Savage Mine. For the assay office, there are monthly inventories noting the quantity and value of office supplies. These reports, by the assayers, D. W. Balih (1871-72) and C. Wiegand (1873-72), are addressed to the superintendent. The property of the Savage mine is documented by annual and monthly inventories; the annual reports list property building by building and the monthly ones note supplies for both Savage and Hale & Norcross. The Savage company maintained a store house carrying everything from timber and lumber to candles, sledges, rope, borax, tar, and hardware. The store house ledgers (Box 63, folders 1064-76) record what supplies are on hand and received during the month. The ledgers also indicate how much (physical and monetary values) of a supply is consumed in extracting ore, prospecting, or improvements. This information is culled from the daily reports (Boxes 63-65, folders 1077-1111). There are specialized inventories for lumber, timber, and wood (lumber, timber, and wood are not synonymous terms in mining records), but they are fragmentary.
Series VI, Pay Roll Records, is arranged by company, and within each company material follows the pattern: ledgers, daybooks (time books), and pay receipts. Since the records are similar, a description of the Savage records will suffice. A Santiago Mill time book is part of a Savage time book and may indicate ownership of the mill by the Savage company (see Box 71, folder 1199). The final official payroll record were the ledgers (Box 70, folders 1178-1182), which cover the period 1861-93 with only a few gaps. Although the format changed over the years, these books usually contain monthly lists arranged by name, noting number of days worked, rate of pay, amount due and paid, and occupation. Positions listed include: pick boy, carman, drifter, wheeler, lamp boy, ore sorter, carpenter, miner, engineer, blacksmith, jackmaker, brakeman, watchman, laborer, boiler man, sampler, foreman, plasterer, oiler, stone mason, giraffeman, driller, caulker, and timekeeper. Comments (such as "Killed by accident, Augt. 11th," "Discharged,") or mentions of assignments and attachments or poll tax payments are often included. The time books (Box 70-75, folders 1183-44) were the daily accounting of employment and usually only note what days a man worked, position, and pay rate. The pay receipts (Boxes 75-79, folders 1246-1343) are signed by employees and document the payment of salaries.
Series VII, Tax Records, arranged by company, consists of county tax statements. These annual reports, recorded on printed forms, have room to note furniture, goods, animals, capital, debts, bullion and gold dust, and real estate, but usually only the real estate holdings are marked. Sometimes only the value is noted, not the tax. For the Savage company there are poll tax records for 1865 indicating that four dollars a year was withheld from each employee's pay check for state taxes.
Series VIII, Mining Company Forms, contains blank forms arranged parallel to the collection.
Series IX, Tailings, is comprised of miscellaneous non-corporate material. There are publications relating to the Democratic party of Nevada, a few contemporary newspaper clippings concerning the Comstock, personal papers of R. P. Keating, and a Storey County tax list of 1889. A book on accounting practices (Box 81, folder 1391) may be useful in deciphering the financial records of the mining companies.
The artifacts in Series X were taken from the old Savage office building in Virginia City.
Oversize (Boxes 82-94), consists of material from Series I-IX in a parallel arrangement.
The Restricted Fragile Papers in Boxes 95-104 consist of originals for which preservation photocopies have been made. The items in boxes 105-13 were microfilmed and replaced by copyflow within the collection. A negative microfilm exists, as well as a positive, but the positive film is missing some frames. The microfilm call number is "MS Vault / Microfilms / 674."
Appendix I: Outline of Collection by Company
ALABAMA MINING COMPANY
---- Series IV. Box 42
ATCHISON MILL
---- Series II. Box 13
---- Series IV. Box 42
---- Series V. Box 63
BOWERS COMPANY
---- Series I. Box 10
---- Series IV. Box 42
BRUNSWICK EXPLORATION COMPANY
---- Series IV. Box 42
BULLION GOLD AND SILVER MINING COMPANY
---- Series I. Box 10
CHOLLAR GOLD AND SILVER MINING COMPANY
---- Series I. Box 10
---- Series III. Box 26
---- Series IV. Box 42
CHOLLAR MILL
---- Series II. Box 12
CHOLLAR-NORCROSS-SAVAGE SHAFT COMPANY also known as the COMBINATION SHAFT COMPANY
---- Series II. Oversize, Boxes 83-84
---- Series IV. Boxes 42-43
---- Series V. Boxes 63, 66
---- Series VI. Box 67
COMSTOCK TUNNEL COMPANY
---- Sutro Tunnel Company
CONSOLIDATED CALIFORNIA & VIRGINIA MINING COMPANY
---- Series III. Box 26
---- Series IV. Box 43
CROWN POINT MINING COMPANY
---- Series II. Box 12
---- Series VI. Box 67
D. G. M. [COMPANY]
---- Series IV. Box 43
EAST SIERRA MINING COMPANY
---- Series VII. Oversize, Box 90
EMPIRE MILL
---- Series II. Box 12
EUGENE DEWEY, STOCKBROKER
---- Series I. Box 10
GOLDEN EAGLE AND ISIS TUNNEL COMPANY
---- Series I. Box 10
---- Series IV. Box 43
GOLDEN EAGLE MINING COMPANY
---- Series I. Box 10
GOULD AND CURRY MINING COMPANY
---- Series I. Box 10
---- Series IV. Box 43
---- Series V. Box 63
HALE AND NORCROSS SILVER MINING COMPANY
---- Series I. Box 10
---- Series II. Box 12, Boxes 14-15, 20-25
---- Series III. Boxes 26-27
---- Series IV. Box 43
---- Series V. Box 63
---- Series VI. Boxes 68-70
---- Series VII. Oversize, Box 90
HIGHLAND MARY MINING COMPANY
---- Series I. Box 10
HILLSIDE WATER COMPANY
---- Series I. Box 10
---- Series IV. Box 43
HOOSIER STATE MILL
---- Series IV. Box 43
JUSTICE MINING COMPANY
---- Series II. Boxes 16-17
---- Series III. Box 27
---- Series IV. Box 43
---- Series VII. Oversize, Box 90
LADY BRYAN MINING COMPANY
---- Series IV. Box 44
---- Series VI. Oversize, Box 89
LADY WASHINGTON MINING COMPANY
---- Series IV. Box 44
M. [MONAHAN] & COMPANY
---- Series IV. Box 44
M & H COMPANY
---- Series IV. Box 44
MEXICAN MILL
---- Series II. Box 12
NEVADA MILL
---- Series II. Box 25
OCCIDENTAL MILL
---- Series IV. Box 44
R.P.K. [R. P. KEATING] & CO.
---- Series I. Box 10
---- Series IV. Box 44
ROCK POINT MILL
---- Series II. Box 25
SAMUEL DIXON, STOCKBROKER
---- Series I. Box 10
SANTIAGO MILL
---- Series II. Box 25
---- Series IV. Oversize, Box 89
SAPPHIRE MILL
---- Series II. Box 25
SAVAGE MINING COMPANY (including SAVAGE MILL)
---- Series I. Boxes 10-11
---- Series II. Boxes 12-25
---- Series III. Boxes 27-41
---- Series IV. Boxes 44-61
---- Series V. Boxes 63-66
---- Series VI. Boxes 70-79, 89
---- Series VII. Oversize, Box 90
SCORPION MINING COMPANY
---- Series II. Boxes 14, 16
---- Series III. Box 41
---- Series IV. Box 61
---- Series V. Box 66
---- Series VI. Box 79
---- Series VII. Oversize, Box 90
SIERRA NEVADA, MEXICAN AND UNION COMPANY
---- Series IV. Box 61
SIERRA NEVADA MINING COMPANY
---- Series III. Box 41
---- Series IV. Box 61
SOUTH COMSTOCK CONSOLIDATED MINING COMPANY
---- Series I. Box 11
SOUTH COMSTOCK MINING COMPANY
---- Series VII. Oversize, Box 90
SUTRO TUNNEL COMPANY
---- Series II. Box 24a
---- Series III. Box 27, 41
T. H. RALSTON, STOCKBROKER
---- Series I. Box 11
THOMPSON MILL
---- Series IV. Box 61
WARD COMBINATION COMPANY
---- Series IV. Box 61
WASHOE MONTE CARLO COPPER COMPANY
---- Series I. Box 11
WHITE & MURPHY
---- Series IV. Box 79
Appendix II: Presidents, Secretaries, and Superintendents
Listed below are the presidents, secretaries, and superintendents for the Savage Mining Company and Hale & Norcross Mining Company based on information from the collection, printed annual reports, and contemporary district directories.
PRESIDENTS OF SAVAGE:
Lent, William. M.1862-64
McAney, Gen. [G.] B.1863 Jun
Bull, Alpheus1867-68
Morgenthau, M.1870 Jul-
Fair, James G.1870-71, 1875
Pritchard, James A.1873-75 Aug
Wallace, George1875 Aug
Wells, George R. 1893, 1896
SECRETARIES OF SAVAGE:
Holmes, E. B.1865, 1868-69 1875-77, 1880-83, 1889, 1894-96
Thorpe, Guy1878
Thompson, A. B.1884-87
Twiggs, John W.1902-04
SUPERINTENDENTS OF SAVAGE:
Morrow, Robert F.1862-1864 Jun
Day, H. H.1864 Jun-Sep
Curtis, Samuel T.1864 Sep-65, 1876 Aug-1877
Bonner, Charles1866-70, 1879
Shamp, T. B.1869 Feb-1871
McClelland, T. J.1870 Jul-Nov
Fair, James G.[1870]-71
Hamilton, Alonzo C.1872-75 Aug
Osbiston, Frank F.1875 Aug-1876 Aug
Gillett, Milton G.1877-79
Kelley, John R. 1880
Buckminster, P. S.1880-81
Keating, R. P.1881-95
Gorham, Harry M.1896-1903
McDonell, A. J.pre-1907
Turney, W. W.1907
PRESIDENTS OF HALE & NORCROSS:
Mann, George S.1866-69
Flood, J. C.1870-74
Congdon, George1874
SECRETARIES OF HALE & NORCROSS:
Lightner, Joel F.1866-74, 1882, 1888
Thompson, A. B.1883, 1885, 1887, 1889
SUPERINTENDENTS OF HALE & NORCROSS:
Thomas, Charles C.1866-69
Fair, James G.1869-70, 1873
Lyman, Dean B.1872, 1882-83
Keating, Robert P.1873-75, 1883-85, 1887-89
Deidesheimer, Philipp1878-79
Silver mines and mining -- Nevada; Stock exchanges -- United States; Comstock Lode (Nev.); Storey County (Nev.); Virginia City (Nev.); Account books -- United States; Agreements -- United States; Bankbooks -- United States; Cashbooks -- United States; Check Stubs -- United States; Checks -- United States; Daybooks -- United States; Deeds -- United States; Insurance policies -- United States; Inventories -- United States; Ledgers -- United States; Letterpress copybooks -- United States; Minutes -- United States; Payrolls -- United States; Receipts -- United States; Silver miners -- Nevada; Stockbrokers -- California; Belknap, Clayton H., 1851-1908; Bonner, Charles; Curtis, Samuel T.; Dewey, Eugene; Dixon, Samuel; Gorham, Harry M. (Harry Motson), 1859-; Haas, B. G.; Haas, Samuel L.; Hamilton, Alonzo C.; Holmes, E. B.; Keating, Robert P., d. 1896; Lent, William M.; Lightner, Joel F.; McKnight, S. P.; Morrow, Robert F.; Pearce, William, fl. 1883-1891; Shamp, T. B.; Thompson, A. B.; Chollar Gold & Silver Mining Company; Chollar-Norcross-Savage Shaft Company; Comstock Tunnel Company; Gould & Curry Silver Mining Company; Hale and Norcross Silver Mining Company; Hillside Water Company; Justice Mining Company (Gold Hill, Nev.); Savage Mining Company (Virginia City, Nev.); Scorpion Mining Company; Sutro Tunnel Company
- Executive Records, 1858-1959; Series I; 15; (11 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Executive Records, contains papers from the superintendents' offices. The first section, General Records, contains material segregated by form, much of which can not be ascribed to a specific company. Following this section is material organized alphbetically by company. Material whose corporate origin can not be identified has been placed at the end of the Series.
  - GENERAL RECORDS
    The material in this section includes correspondence, business papers, and records of legal proceedings from various mining companies. Each group of records is arranged chronologically without regard to corporate origin.
    - Correspondence, 1861-73 (Box 1, Folder 1-17)
    - Correspondence, 1874-79 (Box 2, Folder 18-29)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Oversize, Box 82, folder 1397
    - Correspondence, 1880-84 (Box 3, Folder 30-42)
    - Correspondence, 1885-93 (Box 4, Folder 43-54)
    - Correspondence, 1894-96 (Box 5, Folder 55-58)
    - Correspondence, 1898 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Correspondence, 1901-03 (Box 5, Folder 60-62)
    - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 63-68)
    - Agreements, indentures and deeds, 1858-62 (Box 5, Folder 69-71)
      See also: Oversize, Box 82, folder 1398
    - Agreements, indentures and deeds, 1863-71 (Box 6, Folder 72-75)
    - Agreements, indentures and deeds, 1873-78 (Box 6, Folder 76-77a)
    - Agreements, indentures and deeds, 1880 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - Agreements, indentures and deeds, 1885, 1887 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Agreements, indentures and deeds, 1888-96 (Box 6, Folder 80-83)
    - Agreements, indentures and deeds (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Assignments, 1866-1900 (Box 6, Folder 85-91)
    - Notes regarding mines and mine claims, 1865-96, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 92-95)
      See also: Oversize, Box 82, folder 1399
    - Notes regarding city lots, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 96)
      See also: Oversize, Box 82, folder 1400
    - Subscriptions for the benefit of miners or their families, 1889,1895,n.d. (Box 7, Folder 97-99)
    - Virginia City or Gold Hill, Justice's Court
      - Attachments, 1865-97 (Box 7, Folder 100-03)
      - Coroner's Inquisition: in the matter of E. R. Hoffman, 1887 Nov (Box 7, Folder 104)
      - Coroner's Inquisition: in the matter J. H. Sullivan, 1888 Mar 27 (Box 7, Folder 105)
      - Executions, 1865-95 (Box 7, Folder 106-10)
      - Mayor and Board of Alderman, City of Virginia vs. Thos. Delaney, 1867 Sep 6 (Box 7, Folder 111)
      - Catharine Fox Administratrix...of the Estate of Levin Fox...vs. James M. Nichol and Mary E. Nichol, 1890 Jun (Box 7, Folder 112)
      - Tim Dempsy vs. H. Haas, 1894 Jan 5 (Box 7, Folder 113)
    - Storey County, Probate Court
      - Estate of Nichols F. Scott, 1862 Oct 7 (Box 7, Folder 114)
      - Estate and Guardianship of Robert Henderson, 1862 Dec 3 (Box 7, Folder 115)
    - State of Nevada, District Courts 1st and 3rd
      - H. J. Templeton vs. Jeremiah Job and John A. McBride, 1862 Aug 26 (Box 7, Folder 116)
      - F. V. Drake, et. al. vs. Thomas Delaney et. al., 1865 Jun 15 (Box 7, Folder 117)
      - Estate and Guardianship of Joseph Stephenson, 1865 Sep (Box 7, Folder 118)
      - A. O. Savage vs. Savage Mining Company, 1865 Oct 31 (Box 7, Folder 119)
      - State of Nevada vs. James Warren, 1885 Jul 24 (Box 7, Folder 120)
      - Estate of Andrew Neenan, 1888 Mar 22 (Box 7, Folder 121)
      - Estate of Ellen Byrne, 1890 Jul (Box 7, Folder 122)
      - Thomas Bell vs. Alabama Mining Company, [1890], 1891 (Box 8, Folder 123-24)